A Guide to the Fan District Association Archives 1964-present
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Fan District Association Archives 1964-present
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 14
2.5 linear feet
Fan District Association
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions
Biographical/Historical Information
The Fan District Association (FDA) was organized in October 1961, after several meetings of interested residents during the previous year. FDA purposes, stated in the organization's Articles of Incorporation include "...[T]he FDA shall be dedicated to the preservation and restoration of the urban residential area, known as the Fan District...encourage community interaction and participation among its residents of varying ages, family sizes and life styles and promote the welfare of the Fan District, in particular, and the City of Richmond, in general."
In 1963, the organization began publishing and distributing its newsletter, FANFARE. This publication, distributed throughout the Fan, serves as the organization's main communication tool and includes articles on FDA activities, social events and on the Fan's historic past. It was also in 1963 that the FDA began its first Christmas House Tour of area homes, which has been one of the organization's main fund raising activities
For over 30 years the FDA has been active in both Fan District and city issues. In 1995, the FDA had thirteen separate committees whose activities illustrate the scope of the association's involvement. Committees include ABC Licenses, Code Enforcement, Education/Schools, Safety, VCU Liaison and Zoning. [A 1981 history of the FDA, "The Fan District Association of Richmond, Virginia, Inc." by Samuel J. T. Moore, Jr., is included in the collection]
FDA membership is open to any individual resident who lives or operates a business in the Fan District. The boundaries of the Fan are from the eastern side of North Boulevard on the west to the western side of Belvidere on the east, and from the south side of West Main Street on the south, to the south side of West Broad Street on the north.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes copies of FANFARE, beginning with issues from 1964 and continuing through 2000. Agendas, minutes, and correspondence date primarily from 1983 through 1994. Bylaws, treasurer and committee reports are included in the collection, as well as a 1981 history of the organization, which includes historic information about the Fan District.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials arranged in chronological order
Organization
A significant portion of the collection, when first deposited in SCA, had been divided by month in folders labeled "Agendas, Minutes". The materials were processed keeping this arrangement intact when possible. In addition to agendas and minutes, other materials, including correspondence and the reports of the treasurer and various committees, can be found in this portion of the collection. In some folders correspondence from a previous or upcoming month may be found. This material was kept in the original order preserving the timeliness of which an item may have been acted upon by the FDA. The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject and chronologically therein.
Contents List
- Agenda, Minutes November-December 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes January -August 1985 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes September-April 1985-1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes June 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes July 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes August 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes September 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes November 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes December 1986 (Box 1)
- Agenda, Minutes January 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes February 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes March 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes April 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes May 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes June 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes July 1987 (Box 2)
- Agenda, Minutes August 1987 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes September 1987 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes October 1987 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes December 1987 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes January 1988 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes February 1988 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes March 1988 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes May 1988 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes February 1990 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes July-June 1991-1992 (Box 3)
- Agenda, Minutes May-May 193-1994 (Box 4)
- By-Laws, Background information for FDA Board Members (Box 4)
- "The Fan District Association of Richmond, Virginia, Inc. "by Samuel J. T. Moore, Jr. 1981 (Box 4)
- FANFARE 1964-1974 (Box 5)
- FANFARE 1975-1979 (Box 5)
- FANFARE 1980-1982 (Box 5)
- FANFARE 1982-1983 (Box 6)
- FANFARE 1985-1988 (Box 6)
- FANFARE 1988-1990 (Box 6)
- FANFARE 1990-1993 (Box 7)
- FANFARE 1994-1995 (Box 7)
- Insurance Policy 1987-1989 (Box 8)
- Mailbag January 1983 (Box 8)
- Mailbag February 1994 (Box 8)
- Mailbag March 1994 (Box 8)
- Mailbag April 1994 (Box 8)
- Mailbag May 1994 (Box 8)
- Mrs. Plyer's Nursing Home, 1613-1621 Grove Ave.-Expansion 1988 (Box 8)